Shireizan
in Mutsu
Poor thing...
かわいそうね
Being treated like a deity in a place like this...
こんな所で神様のように特別扱いされちゃって
Almost like me.
まるでわたしみたい
This feels light, and has a good size.
これは軽そうだし　手ごろな大きさ　いいでしょう
This is good.
いえ　悪いのかしら
Or maybe it's bad?
This is Akutou Bita, after all.
何といっても「悪刀·鐚」なのだから
I see...
なるほど　理解したわ
I get it now.
Well, I've gotten my present now, so "hasten to do good"...
じゃあ　手土産もできたことだし　善は急げ
Or maybe "hasten to do bad"?
いえ　悪は急げかしら
Why are you touching me without permission?
何を勝手に　わたしの肌に触っているのですか
You...
この草が草が草が草が草が
Weed. Weed. Weed. Weed. Weed. Weed. Weed.
Weed.
どこか目立つ場所で待っていれば
If I wait in some obvious place, I'm sure they'll come to see me.
きっと向こうから会いに来てくれるはず
I guess it'll be the first time in half a year?
半年ぶりになるのかしら
It'll be good if Shichika has grown a little.
ちょっとは成長していてくれるとうれしいんだけれど
七花
Anyway, I feel rather good.
それにしても　いい気分だわ
いえ　悪い気分かしら
Or maybe I feel bad?
Nanami...
七実　お前は　お前はあまりにも例外過ぎて
You are too exceptional.
I can't raise you...
俺にはお前を育てることはできぬ
Can't raise you...
育てることはできぬ
You are a monster.
お前は化け物だ
You shouldn't have been born.
お前は生まれてくるべきではなかった
Pitiful...
かわいそう
Pitiful girl...
かわいそうな子
You are truly pitiful.
あなたは本当にかわいそう
You can't even die in peace...
あなたは楽に死ぬことさえもできないなんて
Can't even die...
あなたは死ぬこともできず　生きることもできず
Can't even live...
You are a failure of life.
この生き損ない
Someone like you...
あなたは
Like you...
あなたなんて
Someone like you should die.
死ねばいいのに
Worthless.
くだらない
The necromancy used by the holy guards of Shireizan...
死霊山神衛隊の降霊術
I tried it out, but these are nothing but memories.
物は試しにと使ってみたけど
こんなものただの記憶じゃない
Nanami...
七実
Disappear.
消えろ
I don't need you two to tell me that.
あなたたちに言われるまでもないのよ　そんなこと
Akutou
Bita
The Seiryouin Goken
Temple in Tosa
Emonzaemon-dono.
右衛門左衛門殿
What, Strategian-dono?
何だ　奇策士殿
Your job was to show us the way here, correct?
そなたはここまでの道案内が役目だったのであろう
だったらどうだもう帰ってもよいのだぞ
If that's the case, why don't you just return?
Unnecessary.
いらず
Such a concern is unnecessary.
そのような気遣いは必要ない
ふん　そなたとそなたの大事なお姫さまが何をしようと
Well, whatever your dear princess does is none of my business.
このわたしには関係のないことだがな
I just worry for the future of the Intelligence Division when I see you waiting around with so much spare time.
ただ　思いのほかそなたらも暇なのだなと
監察所の将来を憂えただけだ
Needless.
及ばず
Being present here, I am carrying out my duties to their full extent.
わたしはこうしている今も　十全に職務を全うしている最中だ
Being able to see up close what kind of sword it is that you are carrying is an extremely pertinent duty for me.
奇策士殿の刀がいったい　どのような刀なのか
間近で見るだけで十分に　それはわたしの仕事となる
Why do we have to fight?
どうして俺と姉ちゃんがやり合わなきゃならないんだ
Shichika, don't waste my time.
七花　いいかげんにしなさい
Our two spectators have gotten so bored they've started chatting.
観客のお二人が退屈して雑談を始めてしまったではありませんか
This stare down will get us nowhere.
こんなふうににらみ合っていても　始まりませんよ
You're always looking down on me like that.
姉ちゃんはいつもそんなふうに　上から物を言う
I haven't just been playing around for the past half year, you know.
俺だってこの半年　遊んでいたわけじゃねえんだぜ
へぇ　それは見れば少しはそうだ　と分かるけど
I can see that's at least partly true just by looking at you.
I'm much stronger than when I first fought you.
俺は姉ちゃんと１年前に立ち合ったときより　ずっと強くなっている
I don't want to injure you.
姉ちゃんをケガさせたくないんだ
Injure?
ケガ
Don't be so naive.
何を甘いことを言っているの
I said this was a serious duel.
真剣勝負だと言ったでしょう
Come at me to kill.
殺す気で来なさい
To kill...
殺す気って
I see you really have softened up.
やっぱりぬるくなったのね
Honestly...
まったく　最初から心配はしていたのだけれど
I was worried from the beginning that this might happen.
誰のせいなのかしら
Whose fault was it, I wonder?
Was it Uneri Ginkaku-san?
宇練銀閣さん
Tsuruga Meisai-san?
敦賀迷彩さん
Sabi Hakuhei-san?
錆白兵さん
Azekura Kanara-san?
校倉必さん
それとも凍空こなゆきさん
Or was it Itezora Konayuki-san?
Or perhaps...
あるいは　あなたのせいなのでしょうか　奇策士とがめさん
Could it be your fault, Strategian Togame-san?
If you'd just hand over the Shikizaki sword, there wouldn't be any problem!
姉ちゃんがおとなしく四季崎の刀をとがめに渡してくれりゃあ
それで全部丸く収まる
剣士と剣士が向かい合っているのよ
Two swordsmen are facing off against each other.
How could there be no reason to fight?
戦わない理由がどこにあるというの
You're not a swordsman, Nee-chan.
姉ちゃんは剣士じゃないだろ
You may be right.
そうかもしれないわね
I am a sword.
わたしは刀だわ
Are you any different?
あなたは違うのかしら
あなたにとって戦う理由が必要でしょうから
I went to the trouble of obtaining one of Shikizaki Kiki's Deviant Blades because I figured you'd need a reason to fight.
わたしはわざわざ四季崎記紀の変体刀を見つけてきたんじゃない
If you want it, you have no choice but to defeat me.
刀が欲しければ　わたしを倒すしかない
とても分かりやすい方程式でしょう
That's a simple equation to understand, right?
I don't believe father brought you up to prioritize your sister over your owner.
父さんはあなたを
自分の所有者よりも姉を優先するような育て方はしていないはずだけれど
分かったよ
Fine.
Whatever happens is on your hands.
どうなっても知らねえぞ
Hey, Togame.
おい　とがめうん
Give us the signal.
合図　頼むよ
Alright.
そうか
Let the fight...
いざ尋常に
始め
Begin!
Shichika...
七花
I realize we're in the midst of a duel, but allow me to teach you something for the first time in a while.
真剣勝負の最中に何ですが
久しぶりに教育してあげましょう
You are mistaken.
あなたは間違っています
Firstly, even if you have grown stronger than me through the numerous battles you've experienced this past half year,
まずあなたがこの半年数々の戦場を駆け抜け
わたしよりも強くなっていたとしても
in the end it means nothing,
そんなことに意味はありません
because I have these eyes.
わたしにはこの目があります
These eyes which take in everything.
全てをのみ込むわたしの目
When faced with these eyes of mine, your strength becomes mine.
この目にかかれば　あなたの強さはそのままわたしのものとなる
The incredible skill to learn any technique and use it as her own after seeing it once —
一度見た技をそのまま自分のものとして習得できる
恐るべき戦闘技術秘技·見稽古
Hidden technique: Migeika
I can see through any technique, any movement, and any weaknesses...
どんな技も　どんな動きも　どんな弱点も
彼女は何の修行もないままに　ただ見ているだけで
She learned all the Kyotouryuu techniques with no training, simply by watching...
虚刀流の技を全て身に付けてしまっている
Is that really possible?
そんなことがあり得るのか
いや　現に今　七花は翻弄されているではないか
No, the fact that Shichika is currently at her mercy is proof enough.
Kyotouryuu ultimate secret technique!
虚刀流最終奥義
Shichika Hachiretsu!
七花八裂
And even now, just like it was half a year ago, you're suntil much weaker than me...
そして現時点でも半年前と変わらず
あなたはわたしよりもずっと弱い
姉ちゃん　今何をした
Nee-chan...
What did you just do?
あなたの腰を持って放り投げたのよ
I grabbed you by the waist and threw you.
なっバカなこと言うなよ
Don't be ridiculous!
そ　そうだ
R-Right!
姉ちゃんの細い腕で　俺をぶん投げられるわけないだろ
There's no way you could throw me with those thin arms of yours!
確か蝦夷の彼女　凍空こなゆきさんといったわね
That Ezo girl... Itezora Konayuki, was it?
この怪力に覚えがないわけじゃないでしょ
Surely you remember this kind of brute strength.
そなたさては凍空一族の村を
It was you who wiped out the Itezora village?!
ご明察です
Good deduction.
さすがはとがめさん
As expected from you.
七花　気を付けろ　七実はこなゆきの怪力を見取っている
Be careful, Shichika!
Nanami has obtained Konayuki's strength!
いや　こなゆきのような年端も行かぬ童のものではない
No, not the undeveloped strength that Konayuki has...
凍空一族のあろうことか大人の怪力を
She has the full strength of an Itezora adult!
村を襲うことで会得しておるのだ
She gained the ability by attacking the village!
生き残りがいたとは想定外でしたが
I hadn't expected there to be any survivors, but you're correct.
まあ　そのとおりです
凍空の村を滅ぼしたのは　わたしです
It was me who destroyed the Itezora village.
死霊山を壊滅させたってのは聞いてたけどよ
I'd heard that Shireizan was annihilated,
何で
but why did you need to destroy that village?
村を滅ぼす必要があった
踊山でのこともそうだ　それにこの寺でのことだってそうだろ
The same goes for Mt. Odori, and for that temple!
どうしてわざわざ全滅させる必要があった
Why did you go out of your way to destroy them?
姉ちゃんがそんなことしたせいで　こなゆきは
Because of you, Konayuki is...
変わったことを言うようになったわねえ　七花
You say rather strange things these days, Shichika.
雑草をいくらか引き抜いたところで　やいのやいの言われる覚えはないわ
I don't remember you complaining each time I uprooted a weed.
草むしりはわたしの趣味なのよ
Weeding is my hobby.
それとも　七花
Or are you trying to tell me that as a sword, you want to choose who you cut?
あなた刀が斬る相手を選ぼうというの
とがめさん
Togame-san, I may have been mistaken in entrusting Shichika to you.
あなたに七花を預けたのは失敗だったのかもしれませんね
I really thought I could leave him with you without worry...
確か安心して任せたはずなのに
その言いぶりは筋違いだな
You have no right to say that.
わたしの刀をわたしがどのように使おうがわたしの勝手だ
How I use my sword is my choice alone.
そうではないか
Is that not so?
そのとおりですね
I suppose you're right.
確かに筋違いの逆恨みでした
That was unreasonable of me.
閑話休題
Idle talk aside, that's how it is, Shichika.
七花　つまりそういうことよ
この護剣寺にたどりつくまで
I've been through some fairly tough battles on the way here to Gokenji temple.
わたしもそれなりの戦火をくぐり抜けてきている
真庭虫組の方々をはじめ
I started with members of the Maniwa Insect Squad, then the Itezora clan, then the holy guards of Shireizan...
凍空一族　死霊山神衛隊　そしてこの護剣寺で
and finally Gokenji temple.
いろんな人たちと戦わせてもらったわ
I've had to fight a lot of people.
そしてその全てを吸収している
And I've absorbed all of them.
この目でね
With these eyes.
姉ちゃん　まにわにとも戦ってたのか
You fought the Maniwani too?
むちゃくちゃだ
That's crazy...
あなたの七花八裂くらいなら　一度見ればそれで十分
As for your Shichika Hachiretsu, seeing it once was more than enough.
弱点は一度自分で使ってみるまでは分からなかったけどね
Though, I didn't know its weakness until I tried using it.
やっぱり気付いていなかったのね
You really haven't noticed, have you?
よかったわね　七花
Good for you, Shichika — all your opponents up until now were weaklings.
これまでの敵が弱い方ばっかりで
こんな明白な弱点を誰も見抜けなかったのね
None of them were able to see this obvious weakness, after all.
弱点って何だよ
What do you mean "weakness"?
それをあなたに教えてあげるためにわたしは島を出てきたのだけれど
I had left the island to tell you about it...
ふぬけたあなたを見て気が変わったわ
but after seeing how cowardly you've become, I've changed my mind.
教えてあげるものですか
I'd never tell you as you are.
安心しなさい
Don't worry.
あなたに対して真剣勝負などと言ったわたしの方が大人げなかったわ
It was childish of me to say this was a serious battle with you.
今のあなたはわたしと立ち合う資格さえもない
As you are now, you don't have the right to stand against me.
あなたを相手にするのには　この小指１本で十分よ
For an opponent at your level,
my little finger here will do.
思い上がるのも　たいがいにしろ
Don't be so conceited!
Kyotouryuu "Red Poppy" and "Daphne" hybrid striking technique.
虚刀流　雛罌粟から沈丁花まで
打撃技混成接続
ちなみに忍法足軽応用編
Incidentally, I adapted Ninpou: Ashigaru for this.
打撃から全て重さを取り除いておいてあげたわ
I took the weight out of all the blows for you.
わたしがその気だったら
If I wanted to, I could have killed you 272 times over before you hit the ground.
あなたはそうして倒れるまでに２７２回死んでいる
どうしたの　七花
What's wrong, Shichika?
言いたいことがあれば言っていいのよ
If you want to say something, go ahead.
何が小指１本しか使わないだよ
Like hell that was just one finger!
それはあなたが聞き違いをしたのよ
You heard me wrong.
わたしは「この小指１本以外の全てで十分」と言ったの
I said I'd use everything except my little finger.
姉ちゃん　今のどういうことだよ
Nee-chan, what's going on here?
Huh?
とぼけるな　あんな無茶な技
Don't act dumb.
There's no way you could pull off an insane move like striking me 272 times with that body of yours.
姉ちゃんの体力で　２７２回もの打撃を繰り出せるはずないだろ
That's right...
そうだ　七実に唯一弱点があるとすれば　体が弱いこと
Nanami's only weakness is her fragile body.
体力　持久力がないことだ
She has no strength or stamina.
ああ　まだ話してなかったわね
Ah, I hadn't told you about that yet.
こういうことよ
This is how it is.
What!?
何だと
Nee-chan!!
姉ちゃん
そう取り乱さないでちょうだい
Don't get so upset.
悪刀·鐚のこれが正しい使い方よ
This is the way Akutou Bita is meant to be used.
いかずちを帯びたこのくないを体の中央に刺し込むことによって
With this lightning-charged dagger embedded in my chest, my body's weaknesses are forcibly healed.
わたしの病は強制的に癒やされる
無理やり人体を活性化させる　それが悪刀·鐚
It forces the body to rejuvenate.
That's Akutou Bita's focus!
そう　悪刀七実と言うべきでしょうか
Unlike your Shichika Hachiretsu, I no longer have any weaknesses or blind spots.
わたしにはもう弱点も死角もありません
顔を洗って出直してきなさい
Come back when you've improved a bit.
One month earlier,
１カ月前　蝦夷踊山を後にした奇策士とがめと鑢七花は
Togame the strategian and Yasuri Shichika were determined to return to Owari after putting Ezo's Mt. Odori behind them.
今度こそ尾張に戻るつもりだったのですが
陸奥の死霊山にまつられていた悪刀が何者かに奪われたとの知らせを聞き
But upon hearing the news that Akutou, which had been enshrined in Mutsu's Shireizan, had been stolen,
急きょその下手人の足取りを追うこととなりました
they quickly followed the tracks of the culprit.
Tosa
Why are you here?
なぜそなたがここにいる
言わず
Need not say.
Who is this?
誰
He's the henchman of the princess of Owari, Souda Emonzaemon-dono.
尾張のお姫さまの懐刀
左右田右衛門左衛門殿だ
He's very strange.
ひどい変わり者だ
Cannot agree.
うなずかず　あなたに言われたくはない
I don't want to hear that from you.
あの不愉快な女に言われて
I assume that unpleasant woman ordered you to investigate what we're up to?
わたしたちの動向を探っているのであろう
Not wrong.
外れず
Well, that's exactly it, actually.
まぁ　そのとおりだがな　しかしこたびのわたしはただの連絡係だ
However, I'm just here to contact you this time.
How about I tell you where the culprit is hiding out?
下手人の潜伏先を教えよう
That's right, where is the culprit who stole the sword from Shireizan hiding?
そうだ　その死霊山から刀を奪ったやつはどこに隠れておるのだ
Not hiding.
隠れず
The culprit is quite shamelessly staying in the holiest grounds for swordsmen — Gokenji temple in Seiryouin.
ふてぶてしくもその下手人は
剣士の聖地清涼院護剣寺に　居座っておる
否　清涼院護剣寺を乗っ取ったと言うべきか
No, perhaps I should say she has occupied Gokenji temple.
The culprit who destroyed the first class disaster region of Mt. Shireizan,
壱級災害指定地域死霊山を壊滅に追い込み
and who is currently using Akutou Bita to occupy Gokenji temple in the holy grounds of Seiryouin —
今剣士の聖地たる清涼院護剣寺を制圧している
悪刀·鐚の所有者の名は
Yasuri Nanami.
鑢七実
Owari
I have returned.
ただ今戻りました
You're late!
遅い
Always, always late! How long do you intend to keep me waiting?
いつもいつも本当にいつまで待たせる気よ　この愚か者
You fool!
申し訳ありません
My apologies.
And so?
それで　死霊山が全滅したなんてバカげた噂は
How much truth was there to that ridiculous rumor that Shireizan was annihilated?
どこまでが真実だった
All of it.
はっ　それが全て
It was all a lie?
全て嘘だった
It was all true.
全て本当でした
And it wasn't just Shireizan.
いえ　死霊山のことだけにかぎりません
鑢七実という虚刀流の姉　化け物です
Kyotouryuu's older sister, Yasuri Nanami...
She's a monster.
What?
Fuji Woodlands
I wonder what's going on there now.
今ごろはどうなっているのかな
Ah... yes...
はっはい
To think the monster who annihilated Shireizan was Kyotouryuu's elder sister...
死霊山を壊滅させた化け物が　まさか虚刀流の姉だったなんて
It wasn't just Shireizan.
死霊山だけではない
Mt. Odori in Ezo was also likely destroyed by Kyotouryuu's sister, Yasuri Nanami.
蝦夷の踊山もまた
虚刀流の姉鑢七実によって　滅ぼされていたのだろう
According to the information you gathered, anyway.
お主があの後集めてきた情報によればな
Ah... yes...
あっ はい
Yasuri Nanami, the strongest in all Japan, huh...
全日本最強鑢七実か
She annihilated the Itezora clan?
凍空一族を全滅　どうやったらそんなことができるのよ
How is that possible?
She didn't possess Akutou Bita at that point, did she?
その時点じゃそのお姉ちゃんは
悪刀·鐚を所有してはいなかったんでしょ
That merely shows that she was already monstrous to begin with.
はなから十分に化け物だったということです
あの不愉快な奇策士の計画が乱れるのは大いに結構だけれど
I'm quite happy to see that unpleasant strategian's plans being messed up,
but I don't like taking collateral damage.
それでこっちまで巻き添えを食うんじゃたまったもんじゃないわね
What a miscalculation...
何　この計算違い
Dragging Kyotouryuu out to the surface was all well and good,
虚刀流を表の世界に引っ張り出したのはいいけど
but it looks like we also dragged up something terrifying along with him...
ついでにとんでもないものまで引っ張ってきちゃったというわけか
How did it look?
実際のところどうだった
Does Shichika-kun have any hope of winning?
七花君の方に勝ち目は少しでもあるのかしら
None.
ありません
まったくもって　錆白兵どころの話ではないな
Seriously, this is far beyond the Sabi Hakuhei problem...
Gokenji temple is probably under her control by now.
護剣寺も今ごろは彼女の制圧下でしょう
What will that strategian do?
あの奇策士はどうするのか
No matter how cunning her schemes, I doubt they will work on such a true prodigy.
奇策だろうと　本物の天才相手には決して通用しないだろうに
きっ　奇策士は戦うものではありませんから
Strategians don't fight...
But she may be able to come up with some clever idea.
でも　何かいい手を考えるかもしれません
Or rather, all we can do is hope that she does.
というより　僕たちとしてはそう願うしかないでしょう
I don't think that anyone, including yourself, can stand toe to toe with Yasuri Nanami.
鑢七実に太刀打ちできる者は鳳凰さまを含めても　一人もいないかと
Quite frank, aren't you?
はっきりと言うではないか
However, it is as you say.
しかし　お主の言うとおりだな
There are only 4 of the 12 Maniwa Corps heads remaining now.
真庭忍軍十二頭領が今や残り４人だ
We can no longer afford to take any risks.
さすがにこれ以上危ない橋は渡れない
Which means that all we can do is rely on the strategian to defeat that monster...
化け物退治は奇策士に頼るしかないというわけか
冗談じゃないわよね
This really isn't funny...
ちなみにあんたなら鑢七実相手にどう戦う
On the subject, how would you fight Yasuri Nanami?
I wouldn't.
戦いません
I see.
なるほど　それでも戦わなければならない状況に陥ったらどうする
If you were put into a situation where you were forced to fight her, what would you do?
I'd stall for time.
時間を稼ぎますね　あなたが逃げられるだけの時間を
Enough time for you to escape.
Perfect score!
花マル
But as long as Yasuri Nanami possesses Akutou Bitou, we can't turn a blind eye.
でももう　鑢七実が悪刀·鐚を所有している以上　無視はできないのよね
Was that unpleasant woman doing well?
ところで元気だった　あの不愉快な女
Yes.
はい　護剣寺までの道中はうるさいほどでした
She was noisy all the way to Gokenji.
She pretended to trip and kicked me a few times.
偶然を装って何回か地味に蹴られました
She can be pretty childish sometimes...
子供みたいなまねをするわね
Um... Nanami-sama?
あの　七実さま
Will you be eating?
お　お食事は
I'm not in the mood.
そういう気分じゃないわ
Don't worry about it.
構わないの　今のわたしには必要ないことですもの
As I am, it is unnecessary.
The reign of a suitable prodigy, huh...
「ふさわしき天才が君臨する」か
For the holy land of swordsmen, where battle is hailed as the goal in life, the current state of things is certainly fitting.
戦うことを人生の目的とする剣士の聖地としては
確かに今のありさまの方が正しく
One could certainly say that the holy land is now even more holy-like with Yasuri Nanami reigning over it.
鑢七実の手によって
聖地はより聖地らしさを獲得したものといえるが
However...
しかし
Why did I ever think I could win against Nee-chan?
どうして姉ちゃんに勝てるなんて思ってしまったんだろう
There's no way I could.
勝てるはずがないのに
I don't want to see a battle between siblings if I can help it.
わたしはできれば　兄弟対決など見たくはないのだがな
Is there really nothing that will convince you to give up Akutou Bita?
そなたの胸の悪刀·鐚
引き渡してくれる条件はないのか
You've very kind, as usual.
お優しいんですね　相変わらず
I entrusted Shichika to you because you are the way you are,
わたしは確かにそんなあなただからこそ　七花をお任せしたわけですから
so it would be unfair of me to bear a grudge...
恨み言を言うのは筋違いなのですけれど
However, I never imagined that you would treat Shichika quite so humanely.
けれど　まさかあなたが七花をああも人間扱いしてくれるとは
思いませんでしたよ
島にいたときはもうちょっとこう鋭い刀だったのに
Back when he was on the island, he was more of a sharp sword.
Right now he seems more like a rusty one.
今は何だかさびた刀みたい
Rusty, huh...
さびか
Perhaps I should break him?
いっそわたしが折ってあげるべきなのかしら
Don't say such horrible things.
物騒なことを言うでない
何を言うのですか
What are you talking about?
The task you yourself are undertaking involves plenty of horrible killing.
物騒至極極まりない殺し合いをしようとしているのに
So we can't avoid a duel?
真剣勝負は避けられぬか
There's no reason to avoid it.
避ける理由がないのですよ
T-Togame-san?
とっ　とがめさん
ちぇりおー
Cheerio!
How many days do you think have passed now?
あれから何日たったと思っておる
How long are you planning to be like that?
いつまでそうしているつもりだ
I never imagined you'd get that depressed.
そなたがここまで動揺するとはな　実に厄介なやつだ
You're seriously troublesome.
I'm also shocked at how disheartened I am...
俺も自分がこんなふうになるなんて意外だよ
I'm supposed to be a sword.
俺刀なのにな
Come here!
来い
再教育だ
Time for re-education.
Shichika, I originally decided not to ask you this, but...
七花あえて聞くまいと思っておったが
Why did you hide the fact that Nanami was stronger than you?
七実の方がそなたより　強いということをどうして隠しておった
Because I wanted to be your sword.
それは俺がとがめの刀になりたかったからだよ
That's what I thought when you came to the island.
とがめが初めて島に来た日
そう思ったんだ
You might have chosen Nee-chan if you knew she was stronger.
姉ちゃんの方が強いって分かったら
とがめは姉ちゃんを選んじゃうかもしれないじゃないか
たわけか
Idiot!
I'll only say this once, so listen up!
あっ一度しか言わんから　よく聞いておけ
I don't know about half a year ago, but you're the only sword for me now!
半年前ならいざ知らず
今はわたしの刀はそなたしかおらんと思っておるわ
Don't make me spell this out for you, idiot!
こんなこといちいち言わすな　愚か者
Shichika, look at me!
七花　わたしを見ろ
わたしがこれまでいったいどれだけ負けてきたと思っておる
How many defeats do you think I've suffered up until now?
It's nothing to be proud of, but I've lost hundreds— no, thousands of times.
自慢ではないが　数百数千回と負けておるわ
But even so, I've never sat around, doing nothing but being depressed like you are now!
それでも今のそなたのように
何もせずにただ落ち込んでおったことなどないぞ
And I've always won out at the end of the day.
そして最後には必ず勝ってきた
Can't you see what a disgrace you look?
みっともないとは思わんのか
Well, I do feel embarrassed that I lost to Nee-chan.
姉ちゃんに負けたことは恥ずかしいと思ってるけどさ
Stand up!
立て
It's exactly that depression and hesitation that's disgraceful!
そうやって落ち込んでうじうじしていることこそが
みっともないと言っているのだ
I'll ask you just once!
一度だけだ　一度しか聞かん
I won't get mad at you, no matter what answer you give.
そなたがどのような答えを返そうととがめるつもりはない
This is the only time I won't force you to do anything.
このたびばかりは無理強いするつもりはない
So answer me.
だから答えよ
そなた　七実と再戦する気はあるか
Will you have a rematch with Nanami?
ある
I will!
I see.
そうか　ならばわたしが奇策を授けてやる
Then I shall tell you the scheme I've come up with.
まずはそなたの最終奥義　七花八裂の弱点から話すことにしようか
First, we'll start with your ultimate technique.
Let's discuss the weakness of Shichika Hachiretsu.
七花八裂には重大な弱点がある
There is a serious weakness to Shichika Hachiretsu.
I didn't think it had one...
弱点はないと思っていたんだけどな
I'll put it bluntly.
こういっては何だがな
It's a technique you came up with just half a year ago, right?
そなたが半年前に考えたばかりの奥義であろう
Don't you think it would be strange if it didn't have any holes?
穴がない方がむしろ不思議だと思わんか
When you put it that way...
そう言われりゃそうか
This time is exceptional, so I'll get straight to the point.
今回は特別だ　単刀直入に教えてやろう
Okay.
You describe Shichika Hachiretsu as a hybrid technique which releases 7 techniques at once,
七花八裂は七つの奥義を同時に放つ混成接続技だが
同時というのは方便で
but you just say that out of convenience, and in reality, it's just consecutive techniques executed in succession extremely quickly.
実際は目にも留まらぬ速さの連続技だ
That's obvious.
そんなのあらためて言われるまでもないよ
しかしこの奥義正確には連続技足り得ていない
To put it bluntly though, this technique fails as a combination move.
The fourth move "Ryuuryoku Kakou" is in the way.
第四の奥義　柳緑花紅が邪魔なのだよ
I-In the way?
じゃ　邪魔
What are you doing?
何だよそれ
Kyouka Suigetsu, Kachou Fuugetsu, Hyakka Ryouran.
鏡花水月
花鳥風月
百花繚乱
Ryuuryoku Kakou.
柳緑花紅
This one!
これだ
It's an armor-piercing move that nullifies the opponent's defense.
相手の防御力を無効にする鎧通しの技
It's definitely powerful, but the movement you have to undergo to perform it has a large defensive hole.
確かに強力だが　この「ため」の動作に重大なすきがある
The fourth technique, Ryuuryoku Kakou, is unsuitable as a hybrid technique.
第四の奥義柳緑花紅は　混成接続技としては不適格なのだ
Once your opponent knows that, it's simple to defeat it.
それを分かってさえいれば　破ることなどたやすい
My ultimate secret technique had a hole like that?
俺の最終奥義にそんな弱点が
In the end though, your sister went soft on you.
何だかんだいって　あの姉は弟に甘い
She deliberately demonstrated a hybrid move and hinted at the answer.
わざわざ混成接続技を披露して　回答を示唆しておったのだからな
It really is that simple.
と　実に簡単なことなのだ
それゆえに
And that's why she's probably expecting you to improve it before fighting her again.
そなたが技を改良してくることもはっきりと予想されておるだろう
I guess...
そりゃそうか
In the end, we won't get anywhere unless we defeat those eyes.
結局姉ちゃんのあの目を封じないことには
Well, I do have a plan for that.
一応そのための策も練っているのだがな
I've been putting all my effort into thinking one up while you've been shamefully moping around.
そなたがみっともなく落ち込んでいる間にも
わたしは一生懸命考えておったのだよ
I even comforted you, too.
そなたを優しく慰めながらな
ん　ほれ　何とか言ってみろ
Come on, say something.
Togame...
とがめ　ありがとう
Thank you.
Don't look so happy after I bully you!
っ嫌みを言われて喜ぶな
どんな特殊な性癖だ
What kind of fetish is that?
Shichika, all that's left is for you to settle this.
七花　あとは決着あるのみだ
Why is Nanami doing this in such a roundabout way though?
しかし鑢七実　どうしてこんな回りくどいことをする
Why is she forcing the brother she doted on into a duel that he can't win?
散々甘やかしてきた弟に　なぜ勝てるはずのない勝負を強要する
まさか本当に　剣士と剣士が向き合えば
Could it really be that when two swordsmen face each other...
I'm sure she doesn't really believe that one needs no reason to fight.
戦う理由など必要ないと考えているわけではあるまい
Hurry, Shichika.
七花
早く　早くわたしを殺しに来なさい
Hurry up and come kill me...
Like you killed father.
父さんを殺したように
違う　つながらない
No good, they don't chain well.
七つの奥義の順列組み合わせは　５０４０通りだが
Given all 7 techniques, there are 5040 possible combinations,
柳緑花紅を最初に限定した場合は７２０通りになる
but if you restrict yourself to using Ryuuryoku Kakou first, that becomes 720.
その中で　最もすきのない組み合わせ
I need to find the combination amongst those with the fewest holes in it.
Togame-san...
とがめさん
Understood.
あい　分かりました　いいでしょう
That's fine.
Or perhaps that's bad?
いえ　それとも悪いのかしら
Either way works.
どちらにしても
You seem surprised.
意外そうですね
Well, if you accept then I'd be quite happy with that.
まあ受けてくれるなら　こちらとしてもそれに越したことはないのだが
I have no reason to refuse.
断る理由がありませんよ
わたしは刀ですから
I am a sword, after all.
Shichika said that he didn't understand the point of a sword owning another sword.
七花は　刀が刀を所有するなど意味が分からないと言っておったがな
Is that so?
そうですか
Shichika must have gotten over his depression if he's being that cheeky.
七花も生意気なことを言えるくらいには立ち直れたのですね
あの子　死にますよ
That boy will die.
Let's talk a little.
少しお話をしましょう
とがめさんは
Do you know why our father was exiled to the island?
わたしたちの父が島流しにされた理由については知っているのですか
The war ended and he was gracefully segregated, right?
戦乱が終わって　体よく隔離されたのだろう
As an ally it's very dependable, but to have Kyotouryuu fighting against you is too dangerous.
味方にしておけば頼もしいが
そうできなかった場合　虚刀流は危険過ぎるからな
それだけではありません
That's not all.
Father was also accused of murdering mother.
父は母を殺した疑いをかけられてもいたのです
７００番
700!
Mother belonged to one of the 6 Sengoku feudal lords' families, the Tetsubi family.
母は戦国六大名が一家徹尾家ゆかりの女でした
It wouldn't have been any surprise if he were executed.
本来なら打ち首にされてもおかしくない
腐っても大乱の英雄ということで
But given his status as the hero of the rebellion, they were lenient on him.
温情をかけられたということでしょうか
So did he kill her?
殺したのか　鑢六枝は己が妻を
Yasuri Mutsue's own wife?
Who knows?
さあ　真相は今となっては闇の中ですよ
The truth is hidden in darkness even now.
いえ　やぶの中かしら
No, perhaps hidden in the bushes.
The last doctor was like a bush, after all.
最後にかかった医者もやぶだったみたいですし
That joke's not funny.
その冗談は笑えんな
Either way's good.
どちらでもいいのですよ
Or perhaps either way's bad?
いえ　どちらでも悪いのかしらね
Do you understand why I'm telling you this, Togame-san?
わたしがなぜ今こんな話をしているか　とがめさん分かっていますか
鑢家にとって
Are you trying to tell me that it's perfectly natural for family members to kill each other in the Yasuri household?
家族同士の殺し合いなど　日常茶飯事だとでも言いたいのか
Exactly.
そのとおり
720!
７２０番
Now then, shall we see what you're made of, Strategian-dono?
では策士殿のお手並み拝見といきましょうか
今宵はあなたも手を出すのでしょう
You'll be showing your hand tonight, correct?
Well, not your hand, but your knowledge.
いえ　手ではなくて
出すのはあくまで知恵ですか
さて　どうかな
Who knows.
It's useless.
無駄ですよ
あなたがどのような策を練ろうとも
No matter what plan you come up with, it won't get past my eyes.
わたしの目には通用しません
Plans are plans, but what I come up with are schemes.
策は策でもわたしが練るのは奇策だぞ
いいでしょう
Sounds good.
Or maybe it sounds bad?
いえ　悪いのかしらね
そなたのおめめがいくら良かろうとも
No matter how good your eyes are, I will definitely evade them.
必ずわたしはその目をかわしてみせようぞ
まっ　どちらでもいいわ　どちらでも悪いわ
Well, either way is good.
And either way is bad.
I look forward to it.
では楽しみにしておりますよ
Shall we head to the dojo?
道場に向かえばよいのですね
いや　道場ではない
No, not the dojo.
そなたたちの決戦は　道場ではなく戦場でこそ行われるべきであろう
Your fight will be held not at the dojo, but in the arena of battle.
To allow you to settle this once and for all, I'll have you fight in front of the Buddha.
きっちりと決着をつけるためにも
そなたたちにはみ仏の前で戦ってもらうことにする
The Buddha?
み仏
I needn't explain —
言うまでもない
The unprecedented evil decree that General Kyuu proclaimed,
旧将軍が出したかつてない悪法
and the final result of the 10,000 swords he collected in the sword hunt —
刀狩令によって建立された１０万本の刀の集大成
Your fight will be decided in the presence of the Buddha of swords!
刀大仏の前で決着をつけよう
I don't really mind if you want to look at it, so gaze however long you want, Shichika.
別に　そうして眺めていたいなら
いつまでもそうしてくれていてもいいんだけどね　七花
Nee-chan, can I ask one more time?
姉ちゃん　もう一回だけ　言わせてくれないか
No matter how many times you ask, my answer will stay the same.
何度言われても答えは同じよ
あなたがわたしに勝たないかぎり　渡さない　渡してあげない
If you cannot beat me, I will not hand it over or give it up.
あなたが自分の所有者のために　この刀を収集したいというのなら
If you wish to collect this sword for the sake of your owner, you have no choice but to defeat me.
わたしを倒すしかないのよ
Come at me with the intent to kill.
殺す気で来なさい
わたしもあなたを殺してあげるわ
I will also fight to kill you.
少しは研がれてきたようね
It looks like you've become a bit sharper.
けれどまだぬるいかしら
But you're still lukewarm,
neither hot nor cold.
熱くもなければ冷えてもいないわね
What I'm about to perform is a Shichika Hachiretsu that you've never seen.
これから繰り出すのは　姉ちゃんが初めて見ることになる七花八裂だ
１週間前みたいにはかわせない
You won't be able to block it like you did a week ago.
Possibly.
そうかもね
ねえ　七花　あなた父さんを殺したときのこと　覚えてるかしら
Hey, Shichika...
Do you remember when you killed father?
I guess I do...
そりゃ　覚えてるけど
I haven't thanked you for that yet.
あのときのお礼をまだ言ってなかったわね
But I'm not particularly grateful to you for that,
でも別に感謝しているわけではないのよ
so even now I don't intend to say so.
だから今も言うつもりはない
Because, I would have been fine with being killed by father back then.
わたしはあのとき　父さんに殺されてもよかったんだから
I would have been fine with it.
殺されてもよかった　生きていてもしょうがないんだから
There's no point to me living, after all.
Nee-chan, that's—
姉ちゃんそれは
So make sure you kill me now.
だからちゃんとわたしを殺してね
とがめさん
Togame-san.
That's the way it is, so please hurry up and begin the fight.
そういうことですから　早く合図をお願いします
This might be the last time you two get to speak to each other, you know.
これが最後の会話になるかもしれないのだぞ
この期に及んでまだそんなことを
Saying something like that after coming this far...
それとも　時間を稼いでいるのですか
Or perhaps you're trying to buy time?
Does your plan require time to take effect?
あなたの奇策には時間がかかるとか
分かった分かった
Fine, fine.
好きなだけ殺し合え　この刀兄弟が
Go kill each other as much as you like, you sword-siblings.
10...
I won't hold you back anymore. Do whatever you want.
もう止めんよ　好きにしろ
9... 8...
Let the fight...
3... 2...
いざ尋常に
1..
始め
Begin!
0!
So this is their plan.
そういうことか　何が「いざ尋常に」だ
Let what fight begin?
This is just trickery.
本当にほれぼれする手際
３００本のろうそくがまったく同時刻に同時に燃え尽き
All 300 candles must burn out and extinguish at precisely the same moment.
同時に消える
気の遠くなるような計算と仕込みだった
It took meticulous planning and preparation.
How's that?
どうだ見稽古敗れたりだ
We've overcome your Migeika.
Here I come, Nee-chan!
いくぜ　姉ちゃん
Kyotouryuu, ultimate technique!
虚刀流最終奥義
Ryuuryoku Kakou has many blind spots,
すきが多い柳緑花紅
so Shichika just needs to use that technique first.
ならばそれを１撃目にすればいい
If he can complete that part, Shichika's hybrid—
それさえ決まれば七花の混成
No, his forced combination technique becomes perfected.
いや　　強制接続技が完成する
Shichika Hachiretsu Kai!
七花八裂·改
Kyouka
Suigetsu
H
i
k
a
R
k
u
y
o
u
Rakka
Rouzeki
Hyakka
Ryouran
Kinjou
Tenka
Kachou
Fuugetsu
Signs: Shichika Hachiretsu Kai
やったか
Did you get her?
七花
Shichika...
とがめ　　これ
Togame, here.
How's Nanami?
七実はどうなった
Is she dead?
死んだのか
No.
いや　　あんまり勝ったって感じじゃないな
I didn't really get a winning feeling.
Mostly thanks to your scheme.
半分以上とがめの奇策のおかげみたいなもんだ
医者を呼んでくれるか
Can you call a doctor?
Ah, sure.
ああ　分かった
Without Akutou, Nanami's life is in danger...
悪刀なしでは
七実の命は危ないのであったな
Watch out!
目をそらすな
It can't be, but...
まさかとは思うが
It would appear I was too naive.
どうやらわたしの考えが甘かったようね
Nee-chan, don't move!
姉ちゃん動いちゃ駄目だ
Akutou Bita...
「悪刀·鐚」なんて
そんないんちきな刀で己の強さを調整して
Regulating my strength with such a phony sword,
生命力を活性化することで沈静化させ
Dulling my strength by rejuvenating my life force...
Even though it's called "sight training", I was just trying to become a little weaker by using the strength of others.
見稽古なんて言って他人の強さをまとうことで
少しでも弱くなろうとするなんて
Dulling your strength?!
強さを沈静だと
Nee-chan...
姉ちゃん
You mean you've been learning others' moves in order to become weaker?
より弱くあるために
他人の技を見取ってきただと
I...
わたしが　わたしが甘かったわ
I was too naive.
Trying to live a little longer...
少しでも長生きしようだなんて
そんなありさまで真剣勝負だなんて
And in that condition, fighting seriously...
I'm the one who was lukewarm.
ぬるかったのはわたしの方ね
わたしはまだ生きているわ
I'm still alive.
早く殺してちょうだい
Hurry up and kill me.
Nee-chan...
姉ちゃん
Come.
さあ
Stop it!
やめろ
こんなことに何の意味がある
There's no meaning in doing this!
We've already taken Akutou Bita!
すでに「悪刀·鐚」は収集した
It's over!
もう終わったのだ
There's no more reason for you two to fight!
そなたたちがこれ以上戦う理由はない
Be quiet.
うるさい
What?
何を
Your head will come off with the next one.
次はもちろん
首を落とすわ
Togame's hair...
とがめの髪を
Isn't that great?
よかったわね
Now we have a reason to fight.
戦う理由ができたじゃない
I can't forgive that.
許さないぞ　　たとえ姉ちゃんでも
Even if it's you, Nee-chan.
髪の長い女が好みだったの
You prefer girls with long hair?
You're much like father in that respect.
そういうところも父さんによく似てるわね
はっきり言って不愉快だわ
Quite bluntly, it's unpleasant.
だから草のようにむしるのではなく
That's why, rather than plucking grass, I'll scatter you like a flower.
花のように散らしてあげる
Try it!
やってみろ
However, by that point you'll be torn into pieces!
ただしそのころには
姉ちゃんは八つ裂きになっているだろうけどな
You're finally going to go all out?
やっと全力で戦ってくれるのね
虚刀流七代目当主
I am the 7th generation head of Kyotouryuu, Yasuri Shichika!
鑢七花　参る
Here I come!
流派なし　無所属
Without style or school, Yasuri Nanami!
鑢七実　来ませい
Come!
A sword...
刀
姉ちゃん
Nee-chan!
Shichika, my little brother...
七花　わたしの弟
You're finally going to put me to rest.
やっとわたしを殺してくれる
Nee-chan!!
姉ちゃん
虚刀流最終奥義
Kyotouryuu, ultimate technique!
Shichika Hachiretsu Kai!
七花八裂　改
My body isn't able to withstand my full strength.
わたしの体がわたしの全力に耐えられるはずがないのだ
That's obvious.
分かりきっていたことだ
That's why I've been copying others' techniques,
だからこれまで他人の技を見取ってきたのに
か弱くあるために
in order to become weaker.
In order to live just a little longer.
少しでも長生きするために
姉ちゃん
Nee-chan!
ああそういうこと
Ah, is that how it is?
姉ちゃん
Nee-chan!
Is this what happens when a sword tries to use a sword?
刀が刀を使おうとすると　こうなってしまうのか
虚刀流蒲公英
Kyotouryuu: Dandelion!
Hey, father...
何だ　父さん
In the end, I really am a Kyotouryuu.
わたしもやっぱり虚刀流なんじゃない
Well done, Shichika.
ほめてあげる七花
よくぞよくぞ
Finally, finally...
よくもわたしを殺したわね
Good job killing me.
Huh?
あれ　かんじゃったかな
Did I mess up my line?
Kyotouryuu isn't a style that doesn't use swords.
虚刀流は刀を使わない流派ではない
It's a style that absolutely cannot use swords.
決して刀を使えない流派なのだ
Nanami wanted to be killed...
七実は殺されたかったのだな
I wondered why she got involved in our journey, which meant nothing to her...
どうしてこんな意味のない戦いに身を投じ
I thought maybe she had some plan that involved dragging Shichika into it too,
七花をも巻き込もうとするのかと思っておったが
何のことはない
but there was nothing like that.
それだけだったのだ
The reason was simple.
殺されたいと願ったのだ
She simply wanted to be killed.
姉ちゃんは最強だけど
Nee-chan was extremely powerful, but she was too powerful, and her body wasn't made to fight.
最強過ぎて
やっぱり戦える体じゃないんだよ
Her body was so weak because she was too much of a prodigy.
その弱い体は
天才過ぎるせいなんだ
俺はそう思う
That's what I think.
七花八裂の弱点うんぬんなど口実にすぎん
All that talk about Shichika Hachiretsu's weakness was nothing more than an excuse.
Nanami simply wanted to be killed by you.
ただ七実はそなたに殺してほしかったのだ
人として
She wanted to die like an ordinary person.
当たり前に死にたかったのだ
Even so, I didn't want to kill her.
それでも
俺は姉ちゃんを殺したくはなかったよ
Dad, too...
親父にも
I wonder if Nee-chan also wanted to be killed by Dad.
姉ちゃんは親父にも殺してほしいと思ってたのかな
I suppose it's just like she said herself.
本人が言っていたとおりだ
「殺されてもいい」だよ
"I'm fine with being killed."
許容と希望は違うものだ
What's allowed and what you wish for are different.
But I'm sure Nanami loved your father just as much as you did.
しかし
そなたが父を愛していたように
七実も父を愛していたのだろう
Even so, I...
それでも俺は
Can I touch it?
触っていいか
好きにするがよいこの髪好きの変態め
Do what you like, you hair fetish pervert.
くすぐったい
That tickles!
姉ちゃんは髪切るのうまいんだよな
Nee-chan was pretty good at cutting hair, huh?
I suppose so.
確かに
But I guess now both you and I are left with no family.
しかしこれで俺もとがめと同じ
天涯孤独の身の上ってわけだな
天涯孤独
No family?
Don't be dumb.
バカなことを言うでない
そなた　いったいいつの話をしておるのだ
What time period are you talking about?
わたしにはそなたがおるし
I have you, and you have me, right?
そなたにはわたしがいるであろう
あっ　今笑いおったな
You laughed just now!
You laughed!
笑ったであろう
I wasn't really laughing,
いや　笑ったわけじゃねえけど
恥ずかしくねえかそんなせりふ
but weren't you embarrassed saying something like that?
Shut up!
黙れ　ちぇりおー
Cheerio!
Whoops!
おっと　ほらこっちー
Over here!
And so the two of them finally departed for the Yanari Shogun's home territory of Owari.
こうして
２人はいよいよ家鳴将軍家のお膝元尾張へと出発しました
There are five swords left.
残る刀はあと５本
２人の旅の終わりが少しずつ近づいておりました
The end of their journey slowly draws near.
『刀語』今月こよいのお楽しみはこれまでにございます
The story of Katanagatari for this month and this evening ends here.
oide tan tan taan
Come to me Tan tan taan
おいで　ダンダンダン
kotae wo
The answer
答えを　すぐに教えてあげる
sugu ni oshie te ageru
I'll show you right away
ここへ　ダンダンダン
koko he tan tan taan
Here Tan tan taan
hageshiku
Intensively
激しくすべてを返す
subete wo kaesu
I'll give you back everything
やがて　トントントン
yagate ton ton toon
Before long Ton ton toon
hiraita higeki mukaeru deshou
We'll reach the open tragedy
開いた　悲劇　迎えるでしょう
やっと静かに　やっと彼岸へと
yatto shizuka ni
Finally quietly
yatto higan he to
At long last to the next world
静かに
shizuka ni
Calmly
闇解けて　歌流れて
yami hodoke te
Darkness comes untied
uya nagare te
Black night flows
迷子の　体見ないでね
maigo no karada minai de ne
Don't look the lost body
闇連れ連れ
yami tsurezure
Darkness continues
歌惚れ惚れと
uya horebore to
At the black night dreamingly
saigo ni
In my last moment
最後に　誰かを　みていた
dareka wo miteita
I was watching someone
おいしいね
It's tasty, right?
Nee-chan...
姉ちゃん
To die like an ordinary person...
人として当たり前　死んでいく
It's cruel how difficult it is to obtain such a simple thing.
それだけのことはこれほど　難しと思う
なんとか　残酷のことだ
Will Shichika and I be able to die like ordinary people?
私と七花　当たり前死んで行けるだろうか
Now then, our next destination is lake Fuyouko,
さて
次の目的地は
a designated first grade disaster region in Edo.
一級災害指定地　江戸の不要湖
カラクリ人形　相手にどうな戦う
How will we fight a mechanical doll?
こいつ　自身が刀
That thing itself is a sword??
四季崎の変体刀　どっちいうすぎだ
The Shikizaki Deviant Blades have too much design freedom!
次回　刀語　微刀·釵
Next time on Katanagatari:
Bitou
Kanzashi
Bitou Kanzashi
チェスト　いや　ちぇりおー
Chest!
No, Cheerio!!